So, our game is looking
really good now, so
we have the background
that scrolls endlessly.
We have our happy player
who jumps through the
forest as they're avoiding
all these obstacles.
And now what we want to do
is we want to actually make it so
that we can end our game and
send it to a game over screen.
So what we're going to
do is we need to figure
out how we can
actually label all of these
different objects so
that whenever our player
collides with them we
know what we've hit.
One really cool way of doing this
is by using something called tags.
So if you look at the
top right of our inspector,
we have our ground selected and
there's this little button called tag.
And what we can actually do is
create different tags for different things.
So we can actually go
and tag our player as
player, tag our main
camera as our main camera,
we can tag locations,
different things like that.
So we'll actually create our own tag
by clicking add tag under that dropdown.
And you'll see that there's a
tag here that says list is empty.
So this is our list of tags that
we can use that we created.
We haven't made any yet.
So we'll actually go to this little plus
sign on the bottom right of this bar.
And we'll click that and we'll add our
own tag, so we'll call this one ground.
And then we can press enter to save.
And now when we go back to
our ground, oh, that's weird, huh.
So what do you actually have to do is you
go to the tags in your inspector, you click
the dropdown and it brings
up all the different tags
and then you select the
tag that you want to use.
So it doesn't unfortunately automatically
tag something when you create the tag.
So you just have to
make sure you go back into
whatever you want to tag
and apply the appropriate one.
We're going to do the
same thing to our obstacles.
But in this case, since
we have prefabs, we
need to double click
on our obstacles or click
on the obstacle and
click on the open button.
And then you can see
we have another tag here.
So we'll go to click it and it's on
tag right now as we'll add a tag.
And we already have our
ground tag, but we want a new tag.
So we'll create another one.
And we'll call this one obstacle.
Now if we go back to
our hierarchy that shows
us our prefab preview, you
can see the obstacle here.
So if we click that and
then under tags, just
make sure that you
go and tag an obstacle.
And then when we
leave our prefab editor by
using the arrow next to the
obstacle underneath our hierarchy.
And whenever we
create obstacles, it'll have
this tag applied to
it that says obstacle.
So now we need an actual way
to interact with these obstacles.
So we're actually just going to
use our player controller script.
And then in our player
controller script, you can see
that we actually already
have a way to detect collisions.
In this case, we're detecting
a collision on the ground.
So in our player controller
class, this is actually
where we'll just store
the state of our game over.
So we'll just make a
public Boolean for now.
So that way we can see when
our Boolean is true or false.
And we'll name this game over.
So now we have our game over state saved.
And we're actually going down.
And you can see that
we conveniently already
have a way to track
collisions against other
things using our on
collision enter method.
So this is actually the place
where we can compare the
different tags whenever we
run into those objects specifically.
So we'll start actually with the ground
since we already have this variable here.
So if and then our
condition, we're going to use
collision because in
this case, the collision
is actually the object
that we're colliding with.
And then we're going to call
that collisions game object.
And on that game object, we can
compare the current tag that it has.
And we can actually
use a string for that tag.
So we named our ground ground.
Now in our statement,
we can specifically check
when we collide with
a certain game object.
We can check that game
objects tag and see if it's ground.
So now we'll take our
is on ground variable.
And this is where we set it to true.
And now after we've
compared for the collision
of the ground, we can actually
compare for the collision of our obstacle.
So we'll actually use an L statement.
So else, if what we're colliding with
is an obstacle, then we'll do this thing.
So we'll check first
if we're colliding with
the ground, otherwise if what we're
colliding with is an obstacle, we'll do this.
So we can use a debug.log
statement so that we can
see in the editor in Unity
when our game is over.
And then we have that handy
game over Boolean at the top.
So since its default value is
false, now we set game over to true.
So when we go back into Unity, when we play
our game, you should see on the bottom left
that game over pops up and
tells us that we ran into an obstacle.
So we'll just wait for one
of these fun obstacles.
And there's one.
Ooh, missed it.
My farmer's just so excited.
And then we'll hit this one and boom, you
can see there's a game over at the bottom.
So now what you're going to do is you're
going to make sure on your ground that you
add a ground tag by using
the dropdown, adding a tag.
And then in this list, creating a new tag.
And then what you're going to do is you're
going to go into your obstacle prefab.
And then you're going to apply a
tag to this as well called obstacle.
And then just make sure that you apply
the tag before you leave the prefab editor.
And then in your player controller script,
you're going to create a game over variable
so that we know when the
game is over or when it is not.
And then we're going
to change some of our
code in our on collision
enter method so that
we have an if statement to see if the object
that we collide with is tagged as ground,
then we can set is on ground to true.
Otherwise, if the object
we collide with is an
obstacle, then we set
our game over to true.
And we tell our editor in unity
that the game is now over.
Now it's your turn.